Harry C. Oberholser Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Harry C. Oberholser Papers 1856-1960 1920-1945
MSS35071
Oberholser, Harry C. (Harry Church), 1870-1963
8,400 items
25 containers
9.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Ornithologist. Chiefly correspondence with ornithologists and other scientists on bird life and bird specimens of the United States and other countries, Oberholser's work with scientific organizations, and publication of his books and articles.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Aldrich, John W. (John Warren), 1906-1995--Correspondence.; Bailey, Florence Merriam, 1863-1948--Correspondence.; Bailey, Vernon, 1864-1942--Correspondence.; Bell, W. B. (William Bonar), 1877-1949--Correspondence.; Bent, Arthur Cleveland, 1866-1954--Correspondence.; Bishop, Louis B.--Correspondence.; Brandt, Herbert, 1884- --Correspondence.; Cattell, James McKeen, 1860-1944--Correspondence.; Cottam, Clarence, 1899-1974--Correspondence.; Fisher, A. K. (Albert Kenrick), 1856-1948--Correspondence.; Forbush, Edward Howe, 1858-1929--Correspondence.; Grinnell, Joseph, 1877-1939--Correspondence.; Griscom, Ludlow, 1890-1959--Correspondence.; Henshaw, Henry W. (Henry Wetherbee), 1850-1930--Correspondence.; Jackson, Hartley H. T. (Hartley Harrad Thompson), 1881-1976--Correspondence.; Jones, Lynds, 1865-1951--Correspondence.; Keyes, Charles R. (Charles Reuben), 1871-1951--Correspondence.; Kirn, A. J. (Albert J.)--Correspondence.; Langley, S. P. (Samuel Pierpont), 1834-1906--Correspondence.; Lincoln, Frederick Charles, 1892-1960--Correspondence.; Merriam, C. Hart (Clinton Hart), 1855-1942--Correspondence.; Nelson, Edward William, 1855-1934--Correspondence.; Nice, Margaret Morse, 1883-1974--Correspondence.; Oberholser, Harry C. (Harry Church), 1870-1963.; Palmer, T. S. (Theodore Sherman), 1868-1955--Correspondence.; Pearson, T. Gilbert (Thomas Gilbert), 1873-1943--Correspondence.; Preble, Edward Alexander, 1871-1957--Correspondence.; Richmond, Charles Wallace, 1868-1932--Correspondence.; Ridgway, Robert, 1850-1929--Correspondence.; Ridgway, Robert, 1850-1929.; Roberts, Thomas S. (Thomas Sadler), 1858-1946--Correspondence.; Sprunt, Alexander, 1898-1973--Correspondence.; Stone, Witmer, 1866-1939--Correspondence.; Taverner, P. A. (Percy Algernon), 1875-1947--Correspondence.; Taylor, Walter P. (Walter Penn), 1888-1972--Correspondence.; Todd, W. E. Clyde (Walter Edmond Clyde), 1874-1969--Correspondence.; Van Tyne, Josselyn, 1902-1957--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Museum of Natural History--Correspondence.; American Ornithologists' Union--Correspondence.; Cleveland Museum of Natural History--Correspondence.; U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service--Correspondence.; United States National Museum--Correspondence.; United States. Bureau of Biological Survey--Correspondence.; Wilson Ornithological Club--Correspondence.
Subjects
Bird refuges--Illinois.; Birds--United States.; Birds.; Ornithology--Societies, etc.; Ornithology.; Science--Societies, etc.
Places
Bird Haven Sanctuary (Ill.)
Occupations
Ornithologists.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Harry C. Oberholser, ornithologist, were given to the Library of Congress by Oberholser in 1962. Additions were given by the University Archives, University of Illinois Library, in 1969 and 2001.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Harry C. Oberholser are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1870, June 25 Born, Brooklyn, N.Y.
1888 B.A., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1895 1941 Ornithologist, 1895-1914; assistant biologist, 1915-1923; biologist, 1924-1928; and senior biologist, 1928-1941; United States Biological Survey, Washington, D.C.
1904 1910 Professor of zoology, Biltmore Forest School, N.C.
1914 M.S., George Washington University, Washington, D.C. Married Mary Forrest Smith Professor of ornithology, Pennsylvania Summer School for Teachers
1916 Ph.D., George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1919 1939 Lecturer, American School of Wildlife Protection, McGregor, Iowa
1920 1935 Professor of zoology, American University Graduate School, Washington, D.C.
1925 1927 President, Biological Society of Washington, D.C.
1931 Published with S. Prentiss Baldwin and Leonard G. Worley Measurements of Birds. Cleveland, Ohio
1938 Published The Bird Life of Louisiana. New Orleans: [T. J. Moran’s Sons]
1941 1947 Curator of ornithology, Cleveland Museum of Natural History, Cleveland, Ohio
1963, Dec. 25 Died, Cleveland, Ohio
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Harry Church Oberholser (1870-1963) span the years 1856-1960, with the bulk of the material dating from 1920 to 1945. The collection consists primarily of correspondence supplemented by bird counts, membership certificates, printed matter, articles by Oberholser and others, material on African birds, and cards illustrating bird measurements. The papers are in English and organized into four series: General Correspondence, Special Correspondence, Miscellany, and 2022 Addition.
The General Correspondence consists chiefly of letters from ornithologists and other scientists concerning bird life and bird specimens in the United States and other countries, letters concerning Oberholser’s work with scientific organizations, and correspondence concerning his books and articles.
Correspondents include John W. Aldrich, American Museum of Natural History, American Ornithologists' Union, Florence Merriam Bailey, Vernon Bailey, W. B. Bell, Arthur Cleveland Bent, Louis B. Bishop, Herbert Brandt, James McKeen Cattell, Cleveland Museum of Natural History, Clarence Cottam, A. K. Fisher, Edward Howe Forbush, Joseph Grinnell, Ludlow Griscom, Henry W. Henshaw, Hartley H. T. Jackson, Lynds Jones, Charles R. Keyes, A. J. Kirn, S. P. Langley, Frederick Charles Lincoln, C. Hart Merriam, Edward William Nelson, Margaret Morse Nice, T. S. Palmer, T. Gilbert Pearson, Edward Alexander Preble, Charles Wallace Richmond, Robert Ridgway, Thomas S. Roberts, Alexander Sprunt, Witmer Stone, P. A. Taverner, Walter P. Taylor, W. E. Clyde Todd, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, United States Bureau of Biological Survey, United States National Museum, Josselyn Van Tyne, and Wilson Ornithological Club.
The 2022 Addition includes notebooks containing Oberholser's ornithological observations, particularly in the Shelburne Falls, Massachusetts, and Red Bank, New Jersey, areas from 1886 to 1888.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection is arranged in four series:
General Correspondence, 1883-1960
Special Correspondence, 1926-1936
Miscellany, 1889-1958
2022 Addition, 1856-1899
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1883-1960 (Box 1-22)
  Chiefly letters from ornithologists and other scientists concerning bird life and bird specimens in the United States and other countries, letters concerning Oberholser’s work with scientific organizations, and correspondence concerning his books and articles.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - “Aa-Ay” miscellaneous, (11 folders) (Box 1)
  - “Bac-Bal” miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Baldwin, S. Prentiss, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - “Ban” miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - “Bar-Ben” miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Benjamin, Morris (Box 3)
  - Bennett, George (Box 3)
  - Bent, A. Cleveland (Box 3)
  - “Bes-Bez” miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - “Bh-Bis” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Bishop, Louis B., (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - “Bix-Bran” miscellaneous, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Brandt, Herbert, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - “Bras-By” miscellaneous, (9 folders) (Box 5)
  - “Ca” miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Cattell, James McKeen (Box 6)
  - “Cha” miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Chapin, James P. (Box 6)
  - Chapman, Frank M. (Box 6)
  - “Che-Chi” miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Christy, Bayard H. (Box 6)
  - “Chr-Cor” miscellaneous, (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - “Cos-Dy” miscellaneous, (13 folders) (Box 7)
  - “Ea-Fu” miscellaneous, (12 folders) (Box 8)
  - “Gab-Gal” miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Galley, John E. (Box 9)
  - “Gam-Gan” miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Ganier, Albert F. (Box 9)
  - “Gar-Gas” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Gault, Benjamin T. (Box 9)
  - “Gay-Go” miscellaneous, (5 folders) (Box 9)
  - Godfrey, W. Earl (Box 9)
  - Good, Albert I. (Box 9)
  - “Gra-Gre” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Greely, A. W. (Box 10)
  - Gregory, Stephen S. (Box 10)
  - “Gri” miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Grinnell, Joseph (Box 10)
  - Griscom, Ludlow (Box 10)
  - “Gro” miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Gross, Alfred O. (Box 10)
  - “Gu-Har” miscellaneous, (6 folders) (Box 10)
  - “Has-How” miscellaneous, (10 folders) (Box 11)
  - Howell, Arthur H. (Box 11)
  - “Hoy-Hy” miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - “I” miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - “Ja” miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Jackson, Hartley H. (Box 12)
  - “Je-Jo” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Jones, Lynds (Box 12)
  - “Ju-Ke” miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Kemsies, Emerson (Box 12)
  - Kennard, Frederic H. (Box 12)
  - Kermode, F. (Box 12)
  - Keyes, Charles R. (Box 12)
  - “Ki” miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Kirn, Albert J. (Box 12)
  - “Kl-Ky” miscellaneous, (5 folders) (Box 12)
  - “Lab-Lang” miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Langley, S. P. (Box 13)
  - “Lang-Lee” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Leche, R. W. (Box 13)
  - “Leg-Li” miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Lincoln, Frederick C. (Box 13)
  - “Ll-Lo” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Long, Earl K. (Box 13)
  - Low, Seth H. (Box 13)
  - Lowry, George H. (Box 13)
  - “Lu-McS” miscellaneous, (9 folders) (Box 13)
  - “Mae-Mey” miscellaneous, (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - Metcalf, Isaac Stevens (Box 14)
  - “Mic-My” miscellaneous, (6 folders) (Box 14)
  - “Na-Ne” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Nelson, E. W. (Box 15)
  - “Ni” miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - Nice, Margaret M. (Box 15)
  - “No-Pal” miscellaneous, (4 folders) (Box 15)
  - Palmer, T. S. (Box 15)
  - “Pam-Pet” miscellaneous, (6 folders) (Box 15)
  - “Ph-Ras” miscellaneous, (8 folders) (Box 16)
  - Rathbun, S. F. (Box 16)
  - “Rav-Rey” miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Reid, Bessie M. (Box 16)
  - “Rh” miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - “Ric” miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Richmond, Charles W. (Box 17)
  - “Rid” miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Ridgway, Robert (Box 17)
  - “Ril-Rob” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Roberts, Thomas S. (Box 17)
  - “Roc-Row” miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, Jr. (Box 17)
  - “Ru-Shy” miscellaneous, (13 folders) (Box 17)
  - “Si-Sp” miscellaneous, (5 folders) (Box 18)
  - Sprunt, Alexander (Box 18)
  - “St-Stu” miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - Stone, Witmer (Box 18)
  - Strong, R. M. (Box 18)
  - “Su-Sz” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 19)
  - Swenk, Myron H. (Box 19)
  - “Ta” miscellaneous (Box 19)
  - Taverner, P. A. (Box 19)
  - Taylor, Walter P. (Box 19)
  - “Te-Th” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 19)
  - Thayer, John E. (Box 19)
  - Thomas, Charles C. (Box 19)
  - Thompson, E. J. (Box 20)
  - “Ti-To” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Todd, W. E. Clyde (Box 20)
  - “Tr-Wet” miscellaneous, (14 folders) (Box 20)
  - Whitaker, L. M. (Box 21)
  - “Wic-Wil” miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Williams, Arthur B. (Box 21)
  - Williams, George C. (Box 21)
  - “Win-Z” miscellaneous, (5 folders) (Box 21)
  - Unidentified (Box 21)
- Special Correspondence, 1926-1936 (Box 22-23)
  Letters concerning a memorial fund for Robert Ridgway with documents relating to the Ridgway Bird Haven Association and Ridgway Bird Haven Memorial, and letters from students from James Monroe School, Clarendon, Va.
  Arranged by topic.
  - Ridgway Memorial, letters concerning a memorial fund for Robert Ridgway, 1926-1930 (Box 22)
    - “A-C” miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 22)
    - Coffin, Percival Brook (Box 22)
    - Cox, Mrs. T. J., and Mrs. Arthur Crosby (Box 22)
    - “D-M” miscellaneous, (7 folders) (Box 22)
    - “N-Z” miscellaneous, (6 folders) (Box 23)
    - Ridgway Association documents concerning Ridgway Bird Haven Association and Ridgway Bird Haven Memorial, 1929 (Box 23)
  - James Monroe School, Clarendon, Va., letters from school children, 1936 (Box 23)
- Miscellany, 1889-1958, 1889-1959 (Box 23-24)
  Articles, subject files relating to birds, photographs, printed matter, and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged by type of material or topic.
  - Articles, 1938, undated (Box 23)
  - Subject file (Box 23)
    - Biological stains, 1941-1943 (Box 23)
    - African birds, descriptive material on, 1922, undated, (6 folders) (Box 24)
    - Bird anatomy measurement, diagrammatic cards on (loose cards), undated (Box 24)
  - General miscellany, 1893-1945, (4 folders) (Box 24)
  - Photographs, 1889-1943, undated (Box 24)
  - Printed matter, 1897-1958 (Box 24)
- 2022 Addition, 1856-1899 (Box 25)
  Journal, list, notebooks, and puzzle book.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Journal, 1856 (Box 25)
  - List of birds of Hertfordshire, England, by Alan F. Crossman, 1899 (Box 25)
  - Notebooks, ornithological notes, 1886-1888 (Box 25)
  - Puzzle book, undated (Box 25)